BETH: Individuals with autism
have different cognitive strengths
and weaknesses but some find
organising, sequencing and
prioritising really difficult.
They may have deficits in cognitive
function, which is the intellectual
process by which a person thinks, reasons,
understands ideas and remembers things.
JOE: A person with autism may have
problems with processing information,
understanding the consequences of their
actions, understanding the concept of
time, or may be detailed focused and
less able to see the whole picture.
This can affect their ability to
organise, prioritise and sequence.
BETH: If a person is not able to
understand the concept of time, how
can they plan what they need to do
over a day, a week, a month or a year.
This can cause problems in
daily life but can be especially
difficult in education and work.
Problems with time perception can make
life more difficult generally, as it
is an essential part of the way people
make sense of the world around them.
JOE: Problems with time perception can
also cause delayed reaction to certain
stimuli, such as speech and this can
present communication problems such as
not replying to questions or requests,
or saying things later out of context.
Everyday life for an individual with
autism needs strict routines giving
them time to process information.
They need to be helped to develop
strategies to manage their time and
therefore organise their personal
and education and work routines.
BETH: Let’s now hear from someone about
problems with processing information and
how it can affect an individual’s life.